Rhys Llewellyn Thomas

St Edmund Hall Website: https://rhysllthomas.github.io/

Queen's Lane Email: rhys.thomas@seh.ox.ac.uk

University of Oxford, OX1 4AR Linkedin Profile: linkedin.com/in/rhysllewellynthomas

I am an Early Career Teaching and Research Fellow in Economics at St Edmund Hall, University of Oxford. My research focuses on topics in Health Economics. My speciality is in applying econometric methods to health-related research questions. I mainly teach Microeconomics related subjects to undergraduate students at the University of Oxford, however I also teach the probability and statistics component of prelims.

Academic Positions

2021 - 1 1030100 Early Carcer reaching and rescarciffed to be Edinard Hair, University of Oxio	2021 - $Present$	Early Career Tea	ching and Research Fellow -	St Edmund Hall	, University of Oxfor
--	------------------	------------------	-----------------------------	----------------	-----------------------

2021 - Present Associate Member - Department of Economics, University of Oxford

Education

2017 - 2021	Ph.D Economics - University	of Southampton

2016 - 2017 MSc. Economics (Distinction) - University of Southampton

2013 - 2016 BSc. Economics (First Class Honours) - University of Southampton

Working Papers

Spillover Effects of a Diabetes Diagnosis with Emmanouil Mentzakis (Job Market Paper)

Abstract: Diabetes is a unique condition, in that a positive change in lifestyle and behaviour, is both the first line treatment and the recommended method of preventing the disease. It is theoretically possible that by jointly partaking in diabetes treatment, partners of people with diabetes would substantially benefit from their partners' diabetes diagnosis. Using blood data from the Health Survey for England, and a fuzzy regression kink design, we causally estimate the effect of a diabetes diagnosis on health-related behaviours of the individual with diabetes, as well as, their partners. We find that a diagnosis of diabetes results in a significant increase in the probability of exercising and a decrease in the probability of currently being a smoker both for the diabetic individual and their partner. However, we find limited evidence of other lifestyle changes. From a public health perspective, our results are especially important for the evaluation of diabetes related policies, while positive spillovers, particularly within households, should be taken into account in the evaluation process.

Abstract: Using data from the Oregon Health Insurance Experiment (OHIE) we analyse the redistributive impacts of a publicly financed health insurance expansion. We use a residual inclusion methodology combined with quantile, and ordered logit regressions to estimate the heterogeneity in the effects of health insurance across the income distribution. We find that there are indeed redistributive impacts, even in the small income window we have access to, which would otherwise be concealed in a linear regression. Those at the lower end of the income distribution tend to have a substantial increase in their disposable income as a result of health insurance coverage, while those at the upper end see no change in income.

Work in Progress

More doctors, better health? with Thomas Hone & Christopher Millett

Abstract: Previous studies have focused on a binary measure of the Mais Médicos programme, however this clearly masks the potential differences in the effect by intensity of the treatment. We use the Generalised Synthetic Control (GSC) estimator developed by Powell (2019) to estimate the effect of the number of PMM doctors and in doing so eliminate potential bias from comparing treated and non-treated municipalities. Our analysis focuses on the effect of PMM doctors on hospitalisations and mortality. We also analyse the the heterogeneity in the treatment, and use a data-driven approach to uncover the determinants of the effect size. Our analysis allows us to make general claims regarding the impact of a primary care physician expansion, as well as make a claim regarding the optimal allocation of physicians within this PMM to maximise benefit in Brazil.

Teaching Experience

St Edmund Hall, University of Oxford - Tutor

October 2021 - Present

At St Edmund Hall I am a tutor for microeconomics focused undergraduate papers. Since joining St Edmund Hall I have been a tutor for the following papers:

- Economics Prelims Probability and Statistics (2022)
- Core Microeconomics (2021)
- Public Economics (2021)

Average Module Evaluation: 4.1/5

In 2020, I was the lead lecturer for the masters module "Health economics and policy". The course was aimed at MSc. Public Health students whom have had limited exposure to economics beforehand. The course covers the fundamentals of economics and the main contributions to the field of health economics. For this module I gave weekly lectures, structured the module syllabus, compiled module material, and wrote the module assessments.

University of Southampton - Demonstrator

September 2017 - September 2021

Over the course of my PhD studies I was a demonstrator and teaching assistant for various modules on a range of topics, including: foundational microeconomic theory, statistical theory, applied economics and econometrics classes. My teaching evaluations have been excellent throughout that time, and have also improved in recent years. In 2020 and 2021, I was also required to teach courses online, and record seminars.

Teaching Assistant for the following modules:

- Undergraduate Dissertation (2017, 2018, 2019 & 2020)
- Applied Microeconomics 3 (2019 & 2020)
- Masters Dissertation (2019 & 2020)
- Quantitative Modelling in Economics (2019)
- Foundations of Microeconomics (2017 & 2018)
- Principles of Microeconomics (2017 & 2018)

Average Module Evaluation: 4.4/5

Additional Experience

Department for Education - Higher Economic Assistant

December 2018 - April 2019

At the Department for Education I worked on two main projects:

- <u>Timpson review of school exclusion technical note:</u> The analysis in the technical note aimed to estimate non-causal associations between a number of school and pupil characteristics and the probability of being excluded. We were tasked to reduce the bias caused by observable student characteristics. Published report available at <u>this link</u>
- School-level factors associated with disadvantaged pupil performance: This project involved using statistical learning techniques to analyse the factors most associated with disadvantaged pupil performance.

Additional Activities & Responsibilities

Conferences: PhD-EVS Seminar Series (2021)

Royal Economic Society Conference (2021) XXV AIES National Conference (2020)*

30th Congress of the European Economic Association (2020) European Health Economics Association Conference (2020)*

ALdE XXIII Applied Economics Meeting (2020)*

ATINER International Conference on Health Economics, Management & Policy (2020)*

ESRC South Coast DTP Final Year Conference (2019)

Economics PhD Workshop, University of Southampton (2018)

Family Finance Surveys User Conference (2017)

*Conferences I was accepted to but was not able to attend due to the COVID-19 pandemic.

Invited Presentations: Academic Unit of Health Economics, University of Leeds (2022)

Virtual Seminar on the Economics of Risky Health Behaviors, Cornell University (2021)

Public Health Policy Evaluation Unit, Imperial College (2019)

Referee Experience: PLOS ONE (2021)

SSM - Population Health (2020)

Heylion (2018)

Administrative Undergraduate Admissions for PPE & E&M (2021)

Responsibilities: College Advisor to Postgraduate Students (2021 & 2022)

Tutorial Committee (2021 & 2022)

St Edmund Hall Economics Discussion Event Organiser (2021)

Department of Economics Discussion Event Organiser & Panellist (2020)

Internal PhD Seminar Series organiser (2018, 2019 & 2020) South Coast DTP Student Representative (2018, 2019 & 2020)

Economics PhD Program Student Representative (2020)

Undergraduate Economics Programs Validation Student Representative (2020)

Organiser of 1st Southampton Applied Workshop (2019)

S3RI Data Science Reading Group (2019)

Postgraduate Taught Economics Programs Validation Student Representative (2018)

SCDTP Final Year Conference Organiser (2017)

Research: Research assistant to Professor Jackie Wahba and Professor Corrado Giulietti (2020)

Other Competencies

Languages: English (native), Welsh (native).

Software Skills: Stata (Advanced), LATEX(Advanced), R Statistics (Intermediate).

References available upon request